武当道观 中国南部
李金宝
Li Jinbao.
蒙古人
Mongols.
他们已经把北峰的道观毁了
They have already destroyed the temple at North Peak.
- 尼姑们在哪？ - 东面的道观里
- Where are the nuns?  - In the cloisters. East.
记住我们的誓约 战斗到底
Remember the oath. We fight to the end.
得道之人 视生死为一条
Life and death are one thread.
我会保护经卷的
I will guard the scrolls.
李金宝
Li Jinbao!
别杀他
Do not kill him.
大汗会要这个人的
The Khan will want this one.
马可波罗圣诞特辑
百  眼
什么样的道士能够只身杀死
What kind of monk is able to kill,by himself,
我二十五个蒙古勇士
25 Mongol soldiers?
是在你道观里练成的歪门邪术吗
Is it a form of dark magic practiced at your temple?
你永远不会知道的 明白吗
You shall never know, shall you?
你刚才说什么 道士
What did you just say, monk?
你毁坏道观
You destroyed a temple
你所寻求的答案
and all of the ancient
那些古老经卷都被毁掉了
scrolls that contained the answers you seek.
你们这些道士给我南方的敌人提供庇护
You monks were offering shelter to my enemies in South China.
没有人可以藐视可汗
No place defies the Khan.
我再问你一遍
I will ask you again.
如果你不说 就拔掉你的舌头
If you hold your tongue, I will take your tongue.
道观里到底有什么战斗秘诀
What is this fighting art kept secret in a mountain temple?
平和的艺术
The art of peace.
你弄断训练精良的士兵的脖子
You break the necks of trained soldiers,
割开他们的喉咙 像对野猪一样开肠破肚
cut their throats, gut them like wild pigs,
还说是平和
and you call it peace?
你毁掉道观 还说是天数已定
You destroy a temple and call it destiny?
过去的君王可不曾有我这般慈悲
Kings of the past would not have shown you grace.
我 要发动战争的时候
Me, when I make war on a city,
会留所有的工匠一命
I allow the craftsmen to live.
我会征他们入伍 继续生活
I conscript them into service... and they live.
就在这里
Here.
你要给我的战将讲一下那些汉人的秘诀
You will reveal these Chinese secrets to my war ministers.
用汉人的绝招 去攻击汉人
Reveal Chinese secrets... to fight the Chinese.
证明自己有用 就留你一命
Prove yourself useful, you can live.
违反我的规矩
Defy my laws...
就让你死得 比那些和经卷共同消失的道士
you'll die a death far worse than that suffered by the monks
凄惨百倍
who perished with your scrolls.
觉得我下令时候很幽默吗
Oh, you find humor in my decree?
至高的刽子手只有一个
There is only one Supreme Executioner.
那些想要抢占他位置的人
And those who try to take his place
就好像小孩子 模仿手艺精湛的木匠砍树
are like children trying to carve wood as a master carpenter.
多数人都会伤到自己的手
Most will injure their own hands.
你不怕死吗
You do not fear death?
不会苟且偷生
I do not cling to life.
二者大不相同
There is a difference.
带他下去
Remove him.
这位摔跤手外号草原黑野猪
This wrestler is named Black Steppe Boar.
是在塞西亚抓到的犯人
A prisoner captured in Scythia.
知道为什么要给他个野猪的外号吗
Do you know why he is named after the boar?
他们很是相像嘛
His resemblance is extraordinary.
叫他野猪是因为
He is called Boar because
他赤手空拳 杀人无数
he has killed such without a weapon many times.
野猪先动手 他会锁住你
Boar will advance. He will seize you.
你来展示下如何突破控制
You will demonstrate how to break the grasp.
还要蒙住我的眼
You cover my eyes?
就这些吗
Is that just?
大汗想知道你蒙住眼之后要怎么动手
The Great Khan wants a report on how you fight blindfolded.
真是个任性的傻瓜
He is a most capricious fool.
你要不是懦夫 就把这话当面传达给他
And if you were not cowards, you would tell him the same.
闭嘴 臭道士
Quiet, monk!
你杀的那个将军是速不台的儿子
The general you killed was the son of Subutai.
知道这个名字吗 道士
Do you know that name, monk?
不知道
I do not.
曾经效忠成吉思汗的 最伟大的军事将领
Greatest military commander ever to serve Genghis Khan.
你杀了他儿子
You slayed his son.
这是罪上加罪
This is a crime beyond crimes.
但是
Yet...
就像你说的 不会苟且偷生
you do not cling to life, as you say.
死意味着一切皆无
Death means nothing.
一个可汗该怎么做？
What is a Khan to do?
曾经有商人从小亚美尼亚给我带来一只白鹤
A merchant once gifted me a white crane from Lesser Armenia...
一种极其罕见的水鸟
a water bird that was most uncommon...
因为它生下来时候全黑
because it had been born all black.
黑身白鹤
Black white crane.
我知道这是吉兆
I knew it was an auspicious
能给我带来好运 但是
being that would bring me fortune, but...
这只白鹤不愿意待在我的湖里
that black white crane refused to stay on my lake.
总是想飞走
Always, it would fly away.
自然的呼唤而已 你也明白
Just its natural calling, you see.
所以
So...
为了保留它和我的好运
I served him and my fortune...
就砍掉了它一只翅膀
by cutting one wing.
奉天承运
"By law of the Grand Khan,
皇帝诏曰
Lord of Lords..."
你以为我为什么要让你蒙眼搏斗
Why do you think I had you fight blindfolded?
就因为我是任性的傻瓜？
Because I'm a capricious fool?
还是想看看你
Or to see if you are capable
道家的绝技 能不能在黑暗中战斗
of your Taoist secrets and skills while in the dark?
钦此
"So be it."
因为我知道把你带上来的时候
Because I knew the moment you were presented,
肯定不会像一个顺从的画师
you would not be like the obedient painter...
听话的占星术士 满足于饮酒作乐的诗人
the resigned astrologer, the noble poet contented with wine.
你会拒绝服侍蒙古帝国
You would refuse to serve the Mongol Empire.
到今天
To this day...
白鹤依旧留在我的湖边
that black white crane remains on my lake.
它是我的
He is mine...
我心所爱
and he is beloved.
现在准备好
Are you now ready...
向我的战将传授技艺了吗？
to teach my Ministers of Warfare?
给道士上茶
Tea for the monk.
不要把我和你那些神圣的和尚混为一谈
Do not confuse me with one of your holy Buddhists.
是酒
Wine.
你因为杀速不台的儿子接受了惩罚
You were punished for killing the son of Subutai.
永远别忘了
Never forget that.
不会的
I shall not.
武当的道士
The monks of Wudang
花费毕生的精力要达到真正的虚空
spend their lives trying to achieve true emptiness.
但只有当他克服这种虚空
For only when the sage can overcome the self
方能入道
does he enter into the Tao.
这是所有秘密中最为终极的一个
That is a dark mystery beyond all mysteries,
也是你给我的礼物
and a gift you gave to me.
失明
Blind?
现在我能用一百只眼 看这个世界
I now see the world with one hundred eyes.
再给他倒酒
Give him more wine.
我刚吃了你的马
I've just captured your horse.
我知道
I know.
那你还要知道
Then know this.
那里有四座道观
There are four Taoist temples
依旧站立在武当山上
still standing in the Wudang Mountains.
我的人半个月之后会去将其焚烧 夷为平地
My men will go there in a fortnight and burn them to the ground.
我一声令下
At my single command,
你的宗教就会从这世界上消失
your religion can be wiped off the face of this earth.
亦或 它能生存
Or it can live...
成长
grow...
繁荣
thrive...
只要你向我证明它的价值
if you prove its value to me.
就是训练你的战将？
By training your ministers?
还有别人
And someone else.
您一定就是王子了
You must be the prince.
我叫阿尔泰
I am called Altai.
你为何而来？
Why are you here?
上课
Lessons.
你要在这些课里
And what do you intend to teach me
教我什么？
in these... lessons?
我要让你知道 即使是可汗家的儿子
I'm here to teach you that even the son of a royal khan
也能谦卑 向人求教
is capable of humility and learning.
把扫帚拿起来 阿尔泰 给我扫地
Then take the broom, Altai, and sweep my floor.
回答不错 只要你能坚持
Good answer. If only you believed it.
你就是这大千世界花园里的一个流浪的种子
You are a little nomad weed in the garden of the world.
他们希望你长成参天大树
They wish you to grow into a flowering tree.
这样的树最重要的是什么
What is the most important part of such a tree?
众多的分支和开花
The many branches and the flowering.
我说的是传承
I speak of legacy.
啊 谢谢你讲解这个晦涩的比喻
Ah! Thank you for untangling your elusive metaphor.
我们从根开始
We begin with roots.
可以问个问题吗？
May I ask a question?
问
Do.
如果你要在墙上搞书法
If you wish calligraphy on your wall,
干嘛不叫个能看得见的匠人
why not summon a painter who can see?
能读懂我写的这个符号吗
Can you not read the character I made?
是个火的标志
It is a symbol for fire.
有什么问题
Then what is wrong?
- 上下颠倒了  - 没错
- It's upside down.  - Precisely.
这就是功夫耐性的特质 控制
This is the kung fu character for patience, control.
要把这个一直记在脑子里
Remember this in the future, always,
永远不要屈服于怒气
"Never give way to anger."
师父
Sifu?
我的训练还没累到让你闭嘴吗？
Have I not trained you into exhausted silence yet?
今天的课就到这里 王子殿下
Today's lesson is done, My Radiant Highness.
你看不见 我知道 但是
You cannot see it, I know. But...
我向你保证这是一个伟大的汉人工匠
I assure you it has been overseen by a great Chinese architect...
用最珍贵的木材和技艺打造而成
made from the most precious of woods and hides, and--
愚蠢
Imbecile.
谁把这个火字倒着写在这里的
Someone has painted the character of fire upside down.
我写的
I did.
趁着新年这一天
On this day of the New Year...
我把这第四宝堂
I ordain this place the Hall of the Fourth Treasure.
用你百眼的名字命名
I name you Hundred Eyes...
武术大臣
...Minister of Martial Affairs.
还有
And so...
我请你 以武当道士的身份
I ask of you, as a Wudang priest,
给我儿子一个汉人名字
give my son his Chinese name.
史上有五百多回
There have been 500 over time
有人号称权倾中华大地
who have held the name Emperor of All China,
天之子
Son of Heaven.
以血受戒
Ordained by blood,
这些人恐怕
there are those who would
更适合去收拾牛粪
have been better suited to harvest cow dung
而不是掌控这个伟大的帝国
than to rule the greatest empire on earth.
还些类似白银
There are those who were as silver,
一种稀有金属 但比货币值钱
a lesser metal, but worthy of coinage.
还有些人
And then there are those...
像冰冷的石头
like cold stone,
会抑制自己的力量和怒气
who force their strength and fury
得到的却是胆小怕事的名号
and win the title by fear and intimidation.
流血 不足为奇
Blood is nothing.
勇气和精神才成就贤哲
Heart and spirit make the sage.
因此
And by this...
我给这孩子取名为 真金
I give this boy the name Jingim.
赤足真金
"True gold."
那就这样
So be it.
以后他就叫这个名字
He will walk out of here with this name,
把它当成自己的名字
and carry it as his own
也只有那些真正的贤者明白
into a tomorrow only the oracles can see.
至于你 道士
As for you, priest...
这殿堂是你的了
this temple is yours.
马可波罗第二季
2016年 夏季